<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Phoronix</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/</link>
		<description>Phoronix</description>
		
		<atom:link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.phoronix.com/"/>
		<atom:link rel="self" href="http://localhost:3001/?action=display&amp;bridge=Phoronix&amp;format=mrss" type="application/atom+xml"/>
		
	<item>
		<title>Tesla FSD Chip Added To Upstream Linux 5.18 Along With The Raspberry Pi Zero 2 W</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Tesla-FSD-In-Linux-5.18</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Tesla-FSD-In-Linux-5.18</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 12:08:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="ARM -- " src="assets/categories/arm.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; The upcoming &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=search&amp;q=Linux+5.18"&gt;Linux 5.18&lt;/a&gt; kernel has mainline support available for Tesla's full self-driving SoC along with other interesting Arm hardware. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Earlier this year I wrote about &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-Tesla-FSD-SoC-Patches"&gt;Samsung working to upstream Tesla's FSD chip into the Linux kernel&lt;/a&gt;. This work for allowing Tesla's full self-driving chip used in their latest electric vehicles. The Tesla FSD chip is loosely based on Samsung Exynos IP so there is some overlap there and Samsung engineers carried through to get this Tesla FSD support into the upstream Linux kernel. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2022&amp;image=tesla_fsd_car" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is now upstream support in the Linux kernel for the Tesla FSD chip.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Not that most Tesla owners will be trying to load up a new Linux kernel or custom Linux distribution on their FSD system, this upstreaming in turn may lower the Tesla/Samsung maintenance burden moving forward with having less out-of-tree patches to carry for the kernel build in their software environment. The Tesla FSD SoC is made up of three clusters of four Cortex-A72 processor cores and several extra IP blocks. The Linux kernel support code for the Tesla FSD SoC at this stage is just under 4k lines of new code, on top of all the existing Samsung and AArch64 code within the mainline kernel. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2022&amp;image=tesla_linux_518" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tesla FSD SoC support in the mainline Linux kernel!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The Tesla FSD chip support has been mainlined as of last night into the Linux 5.18 kernel with its merge window ongoing. The DeviceTree updates also include adding the Airoha EN7523 networking SoC, Mediatek MT6582 tablet platform, Microchip Lan966 networking SoC, Qualcomm Snapdragon 625/632 SoCs used by the LG Nexus 5X and Fairphone FP3, Renesas RZ/G2LC and RZ/V2L SoCs, and the Samsung Exynos 850 / 7885 SoCs. The &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;item=raspberrypi-zero-2w&amp;num=1"&gt;Raspberry Pi Zero 2 W&lt;/a&gt; is also now supported by the mainline Linux 5.18 kernel. The Rockchip Bananapi-R2-Pro is another Arm SBC added too. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=raspberrypi-zero-2w&amp;image=raspberrypi_2w_4_med" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Raspberry Pi Zero 2 W is also now supported by the mainline Linux kernel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Meanwhile the &lt;a href="https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/torvalds/linux.git/commit/?id=baaa68a9796ef2cadfe5caaf4c730412eda0f31c"&gt;Arm SoC patches&lt;/a&gt; include support for the Cortex-M7 based i.MXRT10xx series, dropping NOMMU ARMv4/ARMv5 platforms, continuing to cleanup the Intel IXP4xx platform code, and other improvements. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Merged on Wednesday night were also the other Tesla FSD support drivers, memory controller updates for Tegra and Mediatek hardware, SCMI firmware interface updates, and improved power management for Mediate kMT81xx / NXP i.MXM8MQ / NVIDIA Tegra hardware.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>GStreamer Lands New NVIDIA Video Encoder Implementation</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=GStreamer-New-NVIDIA-Encode</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=GStreamer-New-NVIDIA-Encode</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 11:31:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="NVIDIA -- " src="assets/categories/nvidia.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; For those relying on software that leverages the GStreamer multimedia framework and you use the NVIDIA proprietary driver stack on Windows or Linux, with the next release you will be able to enjoy a better NVIDIA GPU-based video encoding experience. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;GStreamer has landed a rewritten NVIDIA video encoding implementation. This new NVCODEC implementation works for both Windows and Linux using the proprietary driver's NVENC interface as with the NVIDIA Video Codec SDK that is part of CUDA. The GStreamer NVIDIA bits for both H.264 and H.265 are affected by this new implementation. The new implementation does drop the OpenGL path, RGBA support, and subsampled planar format support, but its new design does allow for better performance. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=2022&amp;image=nvidia_encode_gstreamer_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2022&amp;image=nvidia_encode_gstreamer_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;This new NVIDIA encoder implementation supports zero-copy memory handling for better performance. This new encoder has been tested to perform better than the old NVIDIA encode implementation in GStreamer while also consuming less GPU memory. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;More details on this new NVIDIA encoder implementation for GStreamer via &lt;a href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/gstreamer/gstreamer/-/merge_requests/1997"&gt;this merge request&lt;/a&gt; that landed on Wednesday.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Linux 5.18 Brings Many Networking Changes, New WiFi / Wired Hardware Support</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-Networking</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-Networking</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 10:44:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="LINUX NETWORKING -- " src="assets/categories/linuxnetworking.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; The networking subsystem updates are busy as always with each Linux kernel merge window. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Jakub Kicinski on Wednesday submitted the networking updates for the in-development &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=search&amp;q=Linux+5.18"&gt;Linux 5.18&lt;/a&gt; kernel with the changes as usual being a mix of new hardware support, various protocol improvements, and network optimizations. Some of the Linux 5.18 networking highlights are below. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;On the WiFi side there is now support for Mediatek MT7916 and MT7921U wireless hardware within the MT76 driver. The BRCMFMAC driver meanwhile has added support for Broadcom BCM43454/6 WiFi. The Intel IOSM driver has added support for the Intel M.2 7360 WWAN card. There is also a lot of new wired networking hardware support including for the Realtek RTL83675 and RTL8367RB-VB, Microchip KSZ8563 switches, Netronome NFP3800 SmartNICs, Fungible SmartNICs, and Mediatek MT8195 switches. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Some of the other driver work includes multi-buffer XDP handling in the Mellanox MLX5 driver, the Realtek R8169 driver will now enable ASPM L1.2 power savings if the system vendor flags it is safe, RJ45 ports handling in the Mellanox MLXSW driver, offloading work for the Marvell Presetera Ethernet driver code, various Intel WiFi (IWLWIFI) additions, background radar detection for the Mediatek MT76 driver,  the Realtek RTW89 driver adds AP mode support and 6GHz band coverage. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Most Linux kernel cycles also see new (e)BPF work and for Linux 5.18 that is the case. (e)BPF has added a packaging allocator for BPF JIT images and can lead to more efficient memory use, lower instruction TLB pressure, and other benefits. BPF also adds support for JIT'ing of add/and/or/xor/xchg atomic operations on AArch64.. There are also libbpf API improvements and a range of other enhancements. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;There is also never-ending work on Linux network performance optimizations. For Linux 5.18 there are UDP IPv6 transfer optimizations, yielding up to a 5% improvement on a dummy net device. Additionally there are TSO packet size adjustments so very low latency links like those in data centers can always send full-sized TSO super-frames. Meanwhile the netns dismantling path is as much as five times faster while also having lower memory usage. Within the Intel Ethernet code is also improved AF_XDP performance. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;See &lt;a href="https://lore.kernel.org/lkml/20220323180738.3978487-1-kuba@kernel.org/"&gt;this pull request&lt;/a&gt; for the full assortment of networking updates for Linux 5.18.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Intel IGC 1.0.10713 Adds Ray-Tracing Support</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Intel-IGC-1.0.10713</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Intel-IGC-1.0.10713</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 09:54:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="INTEL -- " src="assets/categories/intel.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; The Intel Graphics Compiler (IGC) that is open-source and used by the driver stacks on both Windows and Linux is up to version 1.0.10713 and with this milestone is functional ray-tracing support in preparation for upcoming Intel Arc graphics processors with hardware ray-tracing support. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Over the past month Intel has been pushing work on ray-tracing shader support into the IGC compiler and culminated today with the IGC 1.0.10713 release where from the compiler side all of the bits are in place. This IGC ray-tracing support appears to be mostly for their Windows driver stack which uses IGC for shader compilation. On the Linux driver side, IGC is currently just used by their Compute-Runtime compute stack for OpenCL and Level Zero. Intel though has said they are looking at using IGC within Mesa in the future, at which point this ray-tracing support will be of use there. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;On the Linux graphics side within Mesa, as covered across numerous Phoronix articles Intel's Mesa developers have already been working on the NIR compiler support, the Intel ANV Vulkan driver ray-tracing extension support, and related plumbing for supporting Vulkan ray-tracing with the forthcoming GPUs. Intel also just recently &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Intel-OpenCL-CLC-Mesa-22.1"&gt;added a tiny OpenCL compiler to Mesa&lt;/a&gt; as they will be using OpenCL code for building acceleration structures for their Vulkan ray-tracing implementation. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Anyhow, back to IGC 1.0.10713, there is the initial ray-tracing compiler work in this release along with various vector back-end improvements, more OpenCL built-in extensions being supported, support for more SPIR-V functions, and a variety of other compiler additions for this LLVM-based Intel graphics compiler stack. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;More details on the v1.0.10713 update via &lt;a href="https://github.com/intel/intel-graphics-compiler/releases/tag/igc-1.0.10713"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Linux 5.18 Graphics Driver Changes From FreeSync Video Mode To New Intel Hardware</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-DRM</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-DRM</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 09:43:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="LINUX KERNEL -- " src="assets/categories/linuxkernel.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; David Airlie has submitted the Direct Rendering Manager (DRM) driver updates for the &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=search&amp;q=Linux+5.18"&gt;Linux 5.18&lt;/a&gt; kernel that includes the many graphics/display driver changes this cycle. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The DRM changes are busy as always with Linux 5.18 work ranging from AMD FreeSync Video Mode being enabled by default to new Intel graphics hardware support and continued enablement work around DG2/Alchemist hardware that will soon be coming to market in the form of the Intel Arc graphics processors. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=AMDGPU-Linux-5.18-First"&gt;AMDGPU's FreeSync Video Mode is now enabled by default&lt;/a&gt;, no longer requiring the FreeSync Video Mode option for enabling. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- Updates in AMDGPU for supporting new IP blocks of GC 10.3.7, SDMA 5.2.7, DCN 3.1.6, and other bits. This is all &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=AMDGPU-More-Linux-5.18"&gt;in preparation for future hardware support&lt;/a&gt;. AMDGPU also now exposes its IP-based discovery data via sysfs. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=AMD-ROCm-CRIU-XDC2021"&gt;AMDKFD adds CRIU checkpoint and restore capabilities&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Intel-Linux-5.18-DG2-G12"&gt;Intel DG2-G12 sub-platform&lt;/a&gt; is added. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- Continued work on Intel DG2/Alchemist discrete graphics support in general including various workarounds, accelerated migration, an async flipping performance optimization, small BAR support, and other functionality. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- Support for higher DisplayPort and eDP bit-rates, but not much more on the open-source NVIDIA driver side this cycle. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-Pull-Intel-i915"&gt;Intel Alder Lake N support&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- The DRM buddy allocator has been moved to core DRM so it can be easily re-used by multiple DRM drivers. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- A new platform driver adding support for privacy screen handling for Chromebook / Chrome OS devices. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- The MSM DRM driver continues supporting additional Qualcomm SoCs. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- The AST DRM driver adds ASpeed AST2600 display support. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- Panfrost DRM has initial dual-core GPU support. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- Improved EDID parsing for deep color handling. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- A display quirk for the GPD Win Max is added. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;- &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-6x-FBDEV-AST2600"&gt;Faster FBDEV operations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;See &lt;a href="https://lore.kernel.org/lkml/CAPM=9tytg5jd_i3z3C5Y1dii2-cgO11Gjgvaq8qoWn3CGfCreg@mail.gmail.com/"&gt;this pull request&lt;/a&gt; for the full list of Linux 5.18 DRM changes.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Linux 5.18 Crypto Has Arm Optimizations, AVX For SM3, Xilinx SHA3 Driver</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-Crypto</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-Crypto</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 09:02:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="LINUX KERNEL -- " src="assets/categories/linuxkernel.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; The crypto subsystem updates have landed in the &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=search&amp;q=Linux+5.18"&gt;Linux 5.18&lt;/a&gt; kernel. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;On the Arm side there are a number of improvements this cycle including Arm NEON AES optimizations and accelerated crc32_be for AArch4. The continued expansion of NEON usage within the kernel is great to see for Arm users. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;On the x86/x86_64 side, the Linux 5.18 crypto subsystem updates bring &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=AVX-SM3-Hashing-Linux-5.18"&gt;AVX-accelerated SM3 hashing&lt;/a&gt;. SM3 is one of the hashing algorithms backed by China with the Chinese Commercial Cryptography Suite. This AVX-optimized version is showing to performance substantially faster than the generic code path for in-kernel SM3 hashing. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Also notable with the Linux 5.18 crypto updates is the introduction of a Xilinx SHA3 driver. This Xilinx SHA3 driver supports their ZynqMP SoC and allows using that SoC's engine for secure hash calculations. See &lt;a href="https://lore.kernel.org/lkml/Yje766s7fIqYg1Tk@gondor.apana.org.au/"&gt;this pull&lt;/a&gt; for the full list of crypto feature updates this cycle. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;While not directly connected to the crypto pull, the Linux 5.18 kernel also pulled in &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-RNG"&gt;the many random number generator (RNG) updates&lt;/a&gt;. However, the change around unifying /dev/random and /dev/urandom has been &lt;a href="https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/torvalds/linux.git/commit/?id=0313bc278dac7cd9ce83a8d384581dc043156965"&gt;backed out&lt;/a&gt; due to some CPU architectures not having enough source of randomness at boot and no jitter entropy.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Andes NDS32 CPU Architecture To Be Dropped In Linux 5.18</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Andes-Tech-NDS32-Removal</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Andes-Tech-NDS32-Removal</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 23:50:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="HARDWARE -- " src="assets/categories/hardware.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; It was just back in 2018 that &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-4.17-Andes-NDS32"&gt;Andes' NDS32 CPU architecture support was added&lt;/a&gt; with the Linux 4.17 kernel. But now with Linux 5.18 the AndesCore NDS32 architecture is being removed over lack of active maintenance. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The NDS32 Linux kernel port has been for supporting older Andes Technology N13 / N15 / D15 / N10 / D10 era processor cores. These processor cores use a 16/32-bit AndeStar RISC-like architecture. This architecture is designed to be performance-efficient with a small footprint for embedded use-cases from IoT to digital signal controls and various other use-cases. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;While AndesCore NDS32 processors are still used in the world today, the lack of active upstream maintenance on the CPU architecture port is leading to its removal. The &lt;a href="https://lore.kernel.org/lkml/CAK8P3a0DeZ4Gx6fOqLkjmA7kNYW5ZHq8BUpWTXXdqdtxcHRNLg@mail.gmail.com/"&gt;asm-generic pull request&lt;/a&gt; for Linux 5.18 drops NDS32. Arnd Bermann sums up the situation as, "&lt;em&gt;The nds32 architecture ends its tenure in the Linux kernel. The hardware is still used and the code is in reasonable shape, but the mainline port is not actively maintained any more, as all remaining users are thought to run vendor kernels that would never be updated to a future release.&lt;/em&gt;" &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2022&amp;image=andes_n10" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andes N10 is one of the CPU designs affected by the NDS32 removal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Further eroding the viability of this port is newer AndesCore processors are 32-bit and 64-bit designs based on RISC-V. Andes Tech's AndesStar V5 ISA is based on RISC-V now and that is the company's path ahead and thus not incentivized to continue maintaining this NDS32 code for their older processors. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Given AndeStar V3 era hardware only appeared in deeply embedded systems, it's unlikely any of you are running NDS32 especially with modern kernels. Out-of-tree kernel ports such as with Andes Tech's SDK still exist as does the NDS32 support still being found in existing Linux LTS kernel series.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Linux 5.18 EDAC Continues Making Preparations For AMD Zen 4</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-EDAC</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.18-EDAC</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 19:18:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="AMD -- " src="assets/categories/amd.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; AMD continues improving their Error Detection And Correction (EDAC) driver code within the Linux kernel ahead of next-generation processors debuting later this year.  &lt;br /&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Linux-5.17-EDAC"&gt;Linux 5.17 AMD EDAC changes&lt;/a&gt; included adding support for Registered DDR5 (RDDR5) and Load-Reduced DDR5 (LRDDR5) system memory and adding in support for new Family 19h models.  &lt;br /&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;With Linux 5.18 there is more AMD EDAC work still focused around these new AMD Family 19h models. There has been some disagreeing with my assessment that AMD Zen 4 will still be Family 19h, but the patch work continues to be pointing to that being the case. Zen 4 looks like it will be in Family 19h -- the same as Zen 3 -- and similar to how Zen / Zen+ / Zen 2 spanned Family 17h.  &lt;br /&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;While these patches do not spell out Zen 4, these model IDs don't match existing AMD CPUs including the &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/vr.php?view=30985"&gt;newly released and exciting Milan-X parts&lt;/a&gt;. The AMD EDAC changes for Linux 5.18 add the ability to set the memory type per DIMM -- not for say DDR5 and DDR4, but the likes of LRDDR5 / DDR5 / RDDR5 memory types across different memory controllers. The other work is setting a new "family flags" bitmask and using new offsets for AMD Family 19h Model 10h. A new bitfield is added for indicating DDR5 memory use on a memory controller.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2022&amp;image=linux_518_edac" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Linux kernel continues preparing AMD code paths around DDR5 support for next-generation platforms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;Besides the EDAC work, there has been thermal monitoring and other additions in recent and ongoing kernels ahead of AMD's next-gen hardware launches. See the &lt;a href="https://lore.kernel.org/lkml/YjhQYeGqsuiXAsSp@zn.tnic/"&gt;EDAC pull request&lt;/a&gt; for more details on the changes that were merged on the Error Detection and Correction front for Linux 5.18.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Apple M1 Performance On Linux: Benchmarks Better Than Expected For Its Alpha State</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/vr.php?view=31000</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/vr.php?view=31000</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt;   &lt;p&gt;Last Friday the crew at Asahi Linux led by Hector Martin released &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Asahi-Linux-Apple-M1-Alpha"&gt;the first alpha release for running Linux on Apple Silicon hardware&lt;/a&gt;. I eagerly loaded up Asahi Linux on an M1-powered Apple Mac Mini knowing the various early limitations of the Linux kernel support that is still settling. Overall the Apple M1 Linux performance ended up exceeding my expectations for the performance in its early alpha state. Here are some benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_1_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_1_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linux running bare metal on an Apple M1 Mac Mini!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The Asahi Linux alpha release allows those with Apple M1 hardware (except for the recent Mac Studio support still being worked on) to run an Arch Linux based distribution on the hardware natviely. The Asahi Linux installer is triggered from within macOS 12.3+ via a script in the Terminal.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_2_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_2_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The Asahi Linux install script allowed for successfully setting up the Linux environment on the Mac Mini while preserving the dual boot support to macOS 12. It worked well and was almost entirely automated except for needing confirmation of actions, etc.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_3_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_3_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not the most helpful error message for indicating not enough disk space...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;One initial issue encountered was I had over-estimated the amount of free space on the Mac Mini... The  Asahi Linux installer didn't provide a useful end-user message with that case over lack of storage. But when hitting the Python error and thinking through the possibilities, I realized the lack of storage space was likely the issue. Indeed after wiping away excess files, the Asahi Linux installer proceeded without issues.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_4_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_4_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The Asahi Linux install experience was quick and easy on this 2020 Mac Mini. There are various known limitations right now of Asahi Linux and the upstream Linux kernel support, such as around the speaker handling, flaky headphone jack, and other features on MacBook. Most notable though is the lack of any 3D/graphics acceleration right now for the Apple M1 GPU. That is being worked on by Alyssa and others but still will likely be some time before their OpenGL Gallium3D driver is squared away as well as mainlining of their DRM kernel driver. Plus there will be the need for a Vulkan driver too after that. So for those depending upon graphics acceleration, this is a major blocker at the moment if wanting to use Asahi Linux as your daily driver but is being worked on the community crew. LLVMpipe though with KDE Plasma did work out fairly robust on the Mac Mini.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_6_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_6_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;The M1 Mac Mini used for this macOS/Linux Apple Silicon benchmarking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Besides the lack of GPU acceleration, another notable area still being worked on is around the M1 power management and performance state handling, including not yet having any CPU boost states working. Some users have also reported their M1 MacBooks running rather warm under Asahi Linux, but that is less of a concern for the Mac Mini or with regard to battery life. In any even with the known limitations for this early alpha release, I was still rather impressed by the M1 Linux performance at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_7_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_7_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;   &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=5e9049b32489&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;First up is a look at macOS 12.3 against Asahi Linux Alpha on the same Mac Mini with its 8 cores / 8GB of RAM / 256GB SSD. The default compiler of each operating system and other defaults were in use on both macOS and Asahi Linux.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=c337bf0aaa0e&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=dc3776c08a0c&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=010e57e98351&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=42e0b2654f82&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=f23da55ee092&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The I/O performance was mixed but it's been found that macOS handles fsync very poorly, so just look at these I/O benchmark numbers rather loosely. In any event, under Asahi Linux I haven't noticed the I/O to be in bad shape or issues like that with this Mac Mini.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=d59d8f014f86&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=f793f9e92195&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=d2538698041b&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=e4a9710c4834&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The WebP image encode performance was competitive between the two operating systems with Asahi Linux even leading in some of these WebP benchmarks. The default compilers (Clang on macOS, GCC on Asahi Linux were used) with the same compiler flags.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=9b46fae6a6e4&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=69f1934767c9&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=cefdd8ba6df2&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=f735ecc169db&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=efb51ad42726&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=44ffc6e091d5&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I really didn't expect Asahi Linux to be competitive with macOS performance on the Apple M1 at this early alpha stage.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=4e20e786320f&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=c7bfeed921a7&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=c32213323010&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=19302d54b4e7&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;But there are areas where macOS is still clearly faster than Asahi Linux due to not hitting the M1 P-core boost states under Linux right now and more work in general for power management / performance tuning.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;   &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=724515e2eecb&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=81b8936a69b0&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=b169a0ac52c4&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Coming up I'll also be looking at Clang on Asahi Linux for ruling out any compiler impact differences between the operating systems, but in any event using the stock compiler on Asahi Linux was working out well for the Apple M1 Mac Mini tests.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=b6d812722b94&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=2ade02eacc2f&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=f3fff15b245f&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=d4d7a544dfb2&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=bf96314c943a&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203221-NE-ASAHI363779&amp;sha=56dabdbfb010&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Overall Asahi Linux on the M1-powered Apple Mac Mini was working out well and genuinely performing better than I expected going into this testing. It will be exciting to see how the performance is once the M1 Linux kernel support is more mature and all the performance / power management items addressed, but even right now Linux on the M1 was delivering good performance even for heavy computational tests.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;   &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=9d88f7646129&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;For those wondering how this Apple Mac Mini with Asahi Linux stacks up against various AMD/Intel processors, I ran some benchmarks against some recent tests I did on various x86_64 CPUs under Ubuntu Linux. So here's a quick look for getting a general sense of where the Apple M1 performance currently compares to x86_64 Linux systems:&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=fe4ec52459cd&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=0c74b807ee82&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=1a4b66d938a9&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=b084a556af13&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=e040d8eb5bec&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;It deopends upon the benchmark, but even with the M1 boost states not yet working under Linux, this Mac Mini was performing decent. It was roughly competing with mid-range AMD/Intel CPUs which is not bad for the early state of the Linux port and this is just a basic Mac Mini with an M1 and not the higher-end M1 Pro/Ultra/Max SoCs.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=e19e6a357a03&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=d0cc49c61472&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;For some of the tested workloads the difference can be from differing AArch64 software quality compared to x86_64.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=14b830c144b2&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;In some areas there isn't AArch64 / NEON optimizations in the upstream software while on the x86_64 side more open-source developers already have their code AVX optimized, etc, so there are ecosystem differences at play.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;   &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=c8a308c1b887&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=9829422d4e3d&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=beec8e803c74&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=3af432bb4450&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=e1930ef9d7a3&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The performance for most benchmarks put the Apple M1 Mac Mini base model between a low to mid-range Intel / AMD x86_64 CPU.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;   &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=42589f8d4411&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=21a92695bc25&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;It will be fun to see how the Apple M1 Linux performance evolves over the months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=8ab3b31992bf&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=ea10bfcfb28e&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=8016beec5c4e&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=c78e1417d460&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=009ee21ecd78&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=91e54d3d073f&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;sha=387aafdfcde8&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;It was quite a decent showing of the Apple M1 for its alpha debut on Linux. See more M1 vs. Intel vs. AMD CPU benchmarks via &lt;a href="https://openbenchmarking.org/result/2203229-NE-X86VSM12577&amp;hgv=Apple+M1+Mac+Mini&amp;sor#results"&gt;this result page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;   &lt;p&gt;The lack of working 3D acceleration will be a blocker for some in being able to use an Apple M1 under Linux as a daily production system. Over the months ahead that should be addressed at least for OpenGL acceleration and we'll see how long before there is Vulkan and a really robust open-source graphics stack available.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_8_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_8_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Even with there being power/performance work still ahead for being able to make the most of the M1, these benchmarks with the Mac Mini did genuinely exceed my expectations for this early alpha state. Running Linux on M1 MacBooks may be a bit less than ideal due to also having to worry about the battery life and cooling concerns among other connectivity limitations with the Asahi Linux, but at least in the case of the Mac Mini this was a great little platform for evaluating the early state of Linux on Apple Silicon.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="//www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_5_lrg" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=apple-m1-linux-perf&amp;image=m1_linux_5_med" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Installing Asahi Linux on the Apple M1.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;With this M1 Mac Mini retailing for $669~699 USD for the 8GB system memory version, it's not too expensive either for those now wanting a rather capable AArch64 Linux system for development purposes, etc. As I figured many would ask, I did also run some benchmarks of the M1 Mac Mini against a Raspberry Pi 400 (both with Raspberry Pi OS 32-bit and 64-bit, given that many still are using 32-bit software on the Raspberry Pi).&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203222-NE-M1RPI821779&amp;sha=cbe673e74db2&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;div style="text-align: center; overflow: auto;"&gt;&lt;object data="//openbenchmarking.org/embed.php?i=2203222-NE-M1RPI821779&amp;sha=c59039fa74de&amp;p=2" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;p&gt;The Apple M1 with Asahi Linux at this stage is already a magnitude faster than the Raspberry Pi 400. See more of the Raspberry Pi vs. M1 benchmarks on &lt;a href="https://openbenchmarking.org/result/2203222-NE-M1RPI821779&amp;sgm=1"&gt;this OpenBenchmarking.org result page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Overall that's where Linux currently stands on the Apple M1 / Mac Mini and it will be fun to see how quickly it evolves with better power/performance optimizations and how long before it could be a system suitable for production use with working 3D acceleration and other support items worked out. There still is the concern whether Apple could ultimately lock down the Apple Silicon hardware or introduce new restrictions moving forward, so Linux users are still at the behest of Apple, but for right now the M1 is proving to be a nice Arm Linux desktop option. Keep in mind these Mac Mini benchmarks are the most basic M1 model available (if wishing to see higher-end M1 benchmarks, consider &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=phoronix_premium"&gt;joining Phoronix Premium&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.paypal.com/donate/?hosted_button_id=EA79CCDLNFJNW"&gt;making a PayPal tip&lt;/a&gt; to help offset the costs to eventually procure a higher-end M1 for benchmarking).&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Those wanting to try out Asahi Linux on Apple Silicon can visit &lt;a href="https://asahilinux.org/"&gt;AsahiLinux.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	<item>
		<title>Imagination PowerVR Rogue GPU Vulkan Driver Merged Into Mesa 22.1</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Mesa-22.1-PowerVR-PVR-Vulkan</link>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Mesa-22.1-PowerVR-PVR-Vulkan</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<description>&lt;div class="content"&gt; &lt;div style="float: left; padding: 0 10px 10px;"&gt;&lt;img alt="MESA -- " src="assets/categories/mesa.jpg" width="100" height="100" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt; In addition to the &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=PowerVR-Series-1-Open-Source"&gt;Imagination PowerVR Series 1 code drop&lt;/a&gt; of their late 90's era driver code, Imagination Tech has managed to successfully land its new PowerVR Rogue "PVR" Vulkan driver in time for &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=search&amp;q=Mesa+22.1"&gt;Mesa 22.1&lt;/a&gt;'s release next quarter. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Earlier this month Imagination went public with &lt;a href="https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=Open-Source-PowerVR-Vulkan"&gt;their open-source PowerVR Vulkan driver work&lt;/a&gt; initially focusing on the GX6250 (Series 6XT), AXE-1-16M (A-Series) and BXS-4-64 (B-Series) GPU designs. That "PVR" Vulkan driver is now in Mesa 22.1 as of Tuesday. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2022&amp;image=powervr_6xt" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PowerVR Series 6XT was announced in 2014.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The 54k lines of new driver code were &lt;a href="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/mesa/mesa/commit/?id=8991e646411b73c1e03278267c80758e921f2352"&gt;merged&lt;/a&gt; for the next Mesa feature release, which should be out as stable around the end of May. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img src="//www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2022&amp;image=pvr_merged" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Besides this Vulkan driver, they are also working on a proper DRM/KMS kernel driver but that is still in-development and hasn't been merged to mainline yet. Imagination is only focusing on Vulkan API support right now as they hope the likes of Zink for OpenGL over Vulkan will prove adequate moving forward. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;How excited are you about &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/opensource?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#opensource&lt;/a&gt; PowerVR graphics in 2022?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Phoronix (@phoronix) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/phoronix/status/1506668634487377927?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 23, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;/div&gt;</description>
		
		
	</item>

	</channel>
</rss>